Mr. President, will you just let me know
when you want me to hit record?
Jennifer, are you ready?
>> Recording in progress.
>> Perfect. Thank you. Good afternoon and
welcome to the August 28th, 2026
uh city council work session. Today's uh
work session is on the Cox Ranch
annexation updates. We hope to hear
plenty of updates on this project. I
think we're all very familiar with it.
Um,
Cindy Delansancy is going to uh chair
the meeting for us and she agreed to for
us to ask questions during the meeting
as we go forward. There will be no
public input at this meeting. This is
simply an educational um process for the
council today. So, Cindy, if you're
ready.
>> Thank you, Mr. President and members of
the governing body. My name is Cindy
Dansancy. I am a lawyer with the law
firm of Holland and Hart. I have the uh
privilege and pleasure of working with
my clients via West Properties as well
as Skybox. Uh with me today, we have Tom
Glymmeer and Jack O'Neal. Uh we have one
other individual coming as well as Gay
Woodhouse is also listed as one of our
presenters today. Uh so with that, we're
just getting our technology uh here so
that that the public can can follow
along. But uh as soon as we get the
computer fired up for um for view, we'll
get right into it. Uh again, I think I
might kick things over to Tom just to do
a little introduc quick introduction
himself and uh get the conversation
started related to the Cox Ranch update.
>> Wonderful. Welcome, Mr. President, thank
you. Members of the council, nice to see
you. We appreciate the opportunity to be
here today.
>> Um, we just came from a uh public open
house over at the library. We had a lot
of great questions and good uh
discussion with uh members of the
community, not just the Rolling Hills
community, but uh local business owners
that uh are interested in the project.
and and uh you know this is uh this is
the fourth uh openhouse event that we've
that we've hosted over the last month
and a half. Uh we've had I I think
really phenomenal uh attendance and a
lot of really thoughtful questions. So
we're by no means going to end it at
four. We intend to have ongoing events
open to the public and uh it's that we
believe that is part of being good
corporate citizens uh being good
community members. So we're uh we're
here today uh to share with you some
updates on uh where where we're at
there. A lot has happened in the in the
four months since we uh were last up
here. And I think uh I think a lot of
positive. So um we just as a as a quick
uh refresher
uh I am Tom Gllymeer with VIA West
Skybox Data Centers uh are [snorts] our
partners Jack O'Neal and Gordon
Kellerman. Um we are co-developers. So
think of us as co- co-developers,
co-owners. Uh we are both
privatelyowned companies. We have a few
partners uh at each firm. Each firm has
about 45 to 50 people. And
uh we so we we are um in in some senses
just traditional developers. You could
think think of us as developers of you
know a a multif family project or
industrial project. Um, you know, we
neither company is is is backed by uh
owned by private equity. Um, so, you
know, I think that's something that
we want to make sure that the community
knows is that is that we're uh we're
small firms at the end of the day. Uh,
we operate primarily in the West and we
like to do business where we feel like
our culture and values fit.
Um,
so timelinewise, we obviously over the
next handful of weeks will be back in
front of council. Um, even if everything
goes as as as we hope, we're still
probably at least a year away from any
kind of groundbreaking.
Um we as as you can see the the our
conceptual layout on the parcel the
parcel is uh over 1100 acres. Um this
was our this is our our intent is to
stay near HappyJack. Uh that's where the
infrastructure is. That's where, you
know, we we what attracted us to uh the
area to begin with was infrastructure
along HappyJack and being adjacent to
the North Range Business Park. Uh we
really feel like uh it's it actually is
challenging to even get utilities u much
up into the parcel. Uh we've been
coordinating extensively with BOPU uh
discussing what water and sewer services
might need to look like.
Uh we've had many conversations and we
have weekly calls with Black Hills in
order to coordinate our uh what the
power generation and service is going to
look like long term. Um
we have
uh engaged with the neighbors not just
in the rolling we've had a number of
folks show up in from the rolling hills
neighborhood uh but also our immediate
neighbors. Uh we've had great
conversations with all of our adjacent
neighbors. Uh we really uh have
appreciated the their willingness to uh
step in and and and build a relationship
w with us. Uh we intend for that to be
long term and we uh are are very excited
about having having such great
neighbors. Um, so maybe with that I
could um, you know, we are working on a
a draft agreement of what a commitment
to the community looks like and and you
know I think that I could maybe hand it
over to Jack here and he could elaborate
a little bit more on, you know, what the
facilities look like, water, power, um,
etc.
>> Absolutely. Uh, first and foremost,
thank you everyone for the time. Thank
you to everybody who came out. um
earlier today as well as uh during our
session now and just appreciate the
opportunity to work together on a Friday
and um especially when it's such nice
weather out. It's good to uh good to get
together. So appreciate the time. Um the
establishment I first and foremost say
is that no rate or cost will be passed
on to any rateayer at the power, water
or sewer level. We're fully paying for
every single cent of that ourselves. Uh
from the immediate startup, from the
capex all the way through operation. um
long term and that's legally binding by
both uh Black Hills. We don't know what
that agreement looks like, but they have
a one-pager that they have on their
website that shares all of that
information and mandates it and they
have for some time. Um and we're working
through that with BOPU right now since
this will be a line extension that's not
existing and I mean the rateayer didn't
ask for us to have a water line so they
shouldn't have to pay for that. So,
we're paying for that. um sewer as well.
And uh and then also any kind of
flushing or any hazardous waste that
would potentially be generated on site.
We're working with a group called
Reworld. Um they have offices all over
the country, but they actually truck out
the closed loop water system um because
based on recent events, I know that's a
a concern to not have that go back into
the municipal water supply. And that
will be purified. The clean water can be
tested and then sent back. So you're not
trucking out all the water. It's just
the dirty stuff and they actually purify
it down to essentially a solid and they
take it to an EDPA certified place in
Tulsa, Oklahoma that is uh all on their
website and there's a great gentleman
also named Jack who's uh the
representative over there I've been
working with and we've been working with
to establish a plan for how to dispose
of something like this and then you get
a certificate of destruction um EPA
certified. So that's uh wanted to get
out ahead of that one as well because
we've heard that's a big concern not
only here but just for the industry as a
whole and hopefully we can be leaders in
that space. Um as far as water
consumption um for example our 30
megawatt data center and it's not quite
linear because it's really toilets and
sinks. Um but we employ about 30
gentlemen and women in Flugerville,
Texas. We used about 126,000 gallons of
water last year. For perspective my
house has no pool. I have one daughter
and two dogs. I'm not using a whole
bunch of water. I used 149,000 gallons
last year. It's not like my water bill
was 600 bucks a month. It's for water,
sewers, and trash. It's less than 200
bucks in any given month. Um, which, you
know, it's still expensive, but um, so
our water use is tremendously low. We
underwite conservatively that each of
our facilities will use around six homes
of water. It'll be about 600,000 gallons
or less. Um, we can very confidently and
safely say it'll use less than 600,000
gallons of water. Um, the only event
that we would use substantial water
would be for fire suppression. If
there's a fire, takes a lot of water to
put it out. Um, that's that's really the
only event and time we would. Um, and
apologize for we're running a few
minutes late from a community
engagement. We just came over from the
library. Um, we also put together and I
had a little bit of bandwidth issues
earlier, but would love to show it's a
quick twominut page two-minute video on
kind of what is our closed loop system
here at Skybox if that's okay with
y'all.
Go ahead.
We'll see if it plays.
My immediate lesson today is that we
have to have this downloaded as well,
not just on our website, but this is
also posted on our website as well as
LinkedIn. Um, I've shared it personally
and we've shared as a firm as well and
um stand by everything in here.
>> Do you have a better way to pull this up
potentially?
Yes, let me try.
>> Yeah, we'll circle back to this in the
interest of time. Um, but apologies for
that while Gordon works on that. But,
uh,
we're just incredibly excited to
hopefully of the opportunity to be here
in Cheyenne. I mean, [clears throat]
we've spent, you know, over the past
just since we started this project,
really kind of getting under contract in
December and January of, you know,
January of this year, uh, a lot of time
up here and it's been a fantastic
community and I think that's shown in no
greater fashion than how they showed up
in our community engagement meetings. We
held very open forum. Um, not we're not
going to have some big fancy silver
presentation. You know, we're going to
have all of our information. in fact
you'd like to know, but also we're here
to answer questions and also hear
concerns. And for an example, like one
thing we learned that myself as a Texan
did not learn. We have a lot of
similarities in culture, but we don't
have the snow y'all have. And a big
concern from the rolling hills residents
was Happy Jack's not really getting
plowed sufficiently. And that's going to
pose an issue to the community, but also
our project, particularly if there's
additional construction traffic. So,
we've already engaged Y Dot. We don't
have a solution in place yet, but we're
adamant to figure out how can we be a
catalyst and front the bill for more,
you know, snow plowing, salting of the
roads, whatever is appropriate. about
working with Rolling Hills. We've heard
just some different things from that
community um from community members to
the west and it's been an amazing
opportunity to engage and you know some
people definitely still have concerns
and questions but a lot of people have
been really open and receptive but also
shared with us some awesome ideas of how
can we be good stewards and safe
business partners to the community and
we're hopefully being you know our goal
is to be quick to listen and slow to
speak on a lot of this.
>> Mr. President, if I may jump in.
Something that I think is important for
um the council and and the public to
know is that is that we are just
structurally set up differently than uh
a lot of other of the data centers that
you see. We we are um small firms,
privately owned. We're doing this
speculatively. It's um it's
we are once we get to a certain point in
putting all of the pieces together, the
framework for a project, then we have
lots of relationships for for capital
and for and customers and and tenants in
our buildings. But long-term our our
model is to own and operate and lease
out data centers. So we are essentially
uh a handful of people um you know
funding and pursuing a project trying to
get to a certain point uh trying to get
the various approvals and and contracts
in shape so that we can then present
that package to our end tenants.
>> And I think a uh we can start to jump
into one of our most common questions is
why Cheyenne? Um, I think we're two
small firms doing two to four good
projects at a time over, you know, 5 to
sevenyear basis. We're not trying to be
everywhere. We culturally align here on
so many reasons from a workforce
standpoint, uh, from a cultural
standpoint, both company, both
personally um, and legislatively. It's
just been a fantastic environment. It's
everyone's open for a dialogue to have a
discussion. We may not agree at the end
of the day, but it's been an
unbelievable experience and uh, truly
enjoyable. Um, but the investment that's
been laid here in the planning of from
fiber infrastructure, from power
generation, from a incredibly skilled
and professional workforce coming out of
the colleges in Wyoming, additionally to
the military base has been a huge reason
for why Wyoming. um the power, the fiber
and the workforce are three of the most
important things particularly from a
when a lot of these facilities are going
to national defense, national security
um whether it be AI which is tied to
those as well or whether it be
teleaalth, Netflix, Spotify to the more
trivial ones as well. Um but
[clears throat]
I will say all that of um a big thing
for Yoming is why Cheyenne Wyoming is
just we've partnered with um a lot of
different communities and these are very
large complicated projects that are
tremendous investment and can be done
incredibly correctly and it's an amazing
benefit to a lot of communities. So
we're blessed to be able to choose where
we're at least trying to go. Um and
that's a big reason why we picked here
is we're going to spend a tremendous
amount of time here. We already have
spent a tremendous amount of time here
and this is somewhere and with people
that we would like to spend a lot of
that time with. Um the need for data
centers has risen obviously incredibly
from the proliferation of AI whether it
be in competition with each other or
China or be proliferation of use of just
our phones and computers, email, what
we're about to show you via video. And
so the the demand has skyrocketed
through the roof. um on all sides and
that's gone up 22% year-over-year from
just a cloud base. Um and then a little
bit more about the project and then also
happy for any questions at any time. So
please feel free to step in and
interrupt. Um but we just wanted to
knock a few things out. Our goal like
Tom said would be to start sometime
hopefully towards the end of next
summer. It's likely about a year if we
were to say get our entitlements. We get
through our power studies with Black
Hills. We start working with local
contractors to get design up and run up
and running and we get all of our long
lead on order. It's it's starting next
year and it's you know going to be a 5
to sevenyear project of you know around
1,000 to500 temporary jobs at its peak.
I would say for the first year you're
ramping at about 200 local jobs that
you're staffing almost entirely locally
coming off of other projects which we
have seen from a lot of people coming at
our community engagement events or
shooting us an email on wyoming at
skyboxdatacenters.com which please feel
free for anyone to reach out. Um the
long-term permanent jobs we're are
anticipating are between 3 and 500. Um
those are anywhere from security to
landscaping to full, you know, technical
directive over all of the MEP equipment
and it's going to be very very skilled
labor jobs that will be highpaying
whether it be HVAC, electrical,
plumbing, leadership, etc. And right now
we're about 32% staffed of um 32%
staffed of veterans. So, our goal is to
also partner with the Air Force base for
people rolling off and staff them
full-time through a program called
Skillbridge, which is an unbelievable
program and we've had the opportunity to
work with considerably before and it's
been great. And these jobs are not, you
know, minimum wage. These are very good,
strong livable wages, generally salaried
positions as well, um, with full
benefits. you know, you're looking at
401ks, healthcarees, um, long-term jobs
with 15-year leases with these hypers
scale clients and multiple five-year
extensions as well.
>> I'll take a breather there for if anyone
has any media questions.
>> Any questions?
>> Do we want to go into the video, Gordon?
>> [clears throat]
>> We can maybe put a mic by it.
>> You see if there's no feedback.
I'm sorry, guys.
often
use a continual water intake and run.
At Skybox, our data centers take a much
smarter approach. We use a closed loop
system that operates a lot like your
car's radiator. Here's how it works. The
system only requires an initial fill of
water to get started around the size of
your local community pool. That cooling
water then travels through a tightly
sealed network of pipes as the computer
ser
>> I shut everything off. I'm really sorry.
>> No worries at all.
>> It doesn't work very well because we
have one remote for five TVs.
>> Mr. President, just a little bit of
context on, you know, some of the
technology glitch. It was absolutely our
intention to come and test out all the
bugs and not have Jennifer running
around the room like crazy. However, at
our um community conversation that we
were hosting, we were having such good
discussion and we certainly didn't want
to rudely abruptly run out of the room
and we were trying to gracefully
gracefully exit to get over here. And uh
um perhaps maybe we need to start that a
little earlier next time. Yeah. Have a
little bit more of a buffer, but um you
know, the the conversation was so well
received and and so robust and and good
and we we certainly maybe just didn't
allow enough time to get over here to
work through some of these kinks. But
while we're working that out, maybe we
come back to our discussion, Jack.
>> Yes, absolutely.
Um
so kind of like uh Tom mentioned earlier
with a little bit uh for what is the
project and where is it located on the
property. You know we're planning two to
three data center buildings. Um they
vary by size depending on the density of
the buildings but our current plan is
about very speculatively it's two to
three buildings on the southwest portion
of the property. um after working with
BOPU on the utilities to serve the site
and we're anticipating with Black Hills
for them to come back that that being
the best area to locate any of the
infrastructure. The way the topography
works from serving it with water, sewer,
power, um ingress and egress for our
operations team that will be hired out
here will all be best served off that
southwest portion of the property.
And uh we can share that we can share
that on the screen here in a little bit
as well. But the
and then additionally on the property
you know it will be you know a small
operations building. We always say we
build enough office and then our ops
team comes back and says hey we're out
of space. So, we've always tried to have
a little bit of room for, you know, an
ancillary office building that's, you
know, not gigantic, but allows for extra
storage, for extra uh, you know, meeting
places, uh, recreational spa space as
well.
For any of the community outreach, Tom,
do you want to take care of that?
>> Sure. Um,
we have I I me I mentioned we've had
great conversations with our neighbors
and we're focusing on the southwest
portion of the site. Um, we we we feel
like um we were a little bit blindsided
to say it lightly um a handful of months
ago with the uh presence of the
mausoleum being on on our property. And
that's something that we were very
grateful to be able to work through with
Miss Woodhouse and and her clients. And
it was great to get to know them and sit
down with them and hear the history of
the ranch and hear what's important to
them and and we have um I I think
finalized an agreement with them that
has a really good outcome at the end of
it. I think for um for not just the
family in the short term but long term
uh preserving that as a
a a landmark.
Um I really appreciate Miss Woodhouse
for being here today. I turn it over to
you for a moment.
>> Thank you. Um council members,
>> welcome. Um, first of all, you know,
this they were blindsided by this and I
I want to go through the history about a
little of how we got here again because
my clients are the true Cox Ranch
descendants and at one point uh Betty
Cox who lived on the ranch her entire
life and died there and is buried in a
casket in the mausoleum uh she lived
with her son Bill Cox lived with her and
he convinced her to transfer some land
west of the home and it included this
mausoleum to him years before her death.
So, uh, in terms of the rest of the
family, there was no real concern about
the mausoleum being properly, you know,
taken care of because William Cox is
also buried there in a casket. So it
wasn't until all of this annexation came
up and they looked at it and saw that it
included the part that had the mausoleum
that you know we were all stunned that
that would have been included especially
because you know Bill Cox is also buried
there. But uh what I will say is that
they have stepped up in a tremendous
way. Um they were surprised but they
rose to the occasion. I'm saying
immediately immediately they wanted to
have meetings. We met together. They
listened to all of my clients concerns.
I mean, they had a lot of concerns. You
know, what about the actual land that it
sits on? How much land do we need around
that? There's fencing there that needs
to be handled. And and they wanted
decorative fencing, which is they
accommodated. I mean, it's going to be a
designed fence and not to mention the
road that comes up from from HappyJack,
which will now be an exclusive rightway.
and will have a gate that they can only
they can access just the family. So, um
I can't um uh overstate the generosity
that they engaged in with us and not to
mention the sensitivity and the
accommodations that they did. Uh it is
my clients are very satisfied. They have
a family
um foundation called Chalk Bluffs
Foundation that's formed in Colorado
that in involves the entire family, the
Cox family, Ketchums and so forth.
And that is going to be the recipient of
the land and the ride ofway and the
moselum. So they it will be kept in
perpetuity in that foundation that they
had already created many years ago. It
was um it was actually a pleasure, you
know, to work with them and and to have
people that really wanted to sit down
and and discuss each and every detail
and really cared about it. So, we
appreciate it.
>> We appreciate you and [snorts] the whole
family. It it was truly a blessing to be
able to work with y'all and uh thank you
for letting us hopefully be a catalyst
for a positive situation that uh you
know previously was not ideal and now
hopefully it ends up in a wonderful
outcome for for all parties. So we're
we're incredibly excited to hopefully be
a be a help to the solution.
>> Sure. Thank you.
>> Questions for Miss Woodhouse?
>> Anyone?
>> I I had a question before a previous
item. So,
>> okay. Thank you. Appreciate it.
>> Wait, wait, G. Sorry.
>> Yeah, Mr. President, through you. I do
have one question, Mr. Woodhouse. Um, is
has that agreement between uh Skybox and
the family? Has that been finalized?
>> It's finalized. Yes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Absolutely.
>> Thank you, Miss Woodhouse.
>> Uh, we do have a question. Not on the
not on the mausoleum. Dr. Aldridge. Um,
President Crave through you to Mr.
O'Neal. Um, as you were describing the
distance, this location in the southwest
corner and the distance from what I
believe to the right of this on the
diagram is Rolling Hills. What is the
from the corner of the most uh western
property in on the diagram um the
residential property to the actual
building is the what is the that
distance?
>> Yes, ma'am. I'll from the Oh, sorry. Uh
Mr. President, through you. Apologies.
Thank you.
>> Um Mr. present through you. The furthest
eastern boundary that corner that kind
of adjuts on that eastern boundary of
the current property to the furthest
western corner on the rolling hills
property is about 1500 ft. If that was
just corner to corner, no setbacks, no
distance. If you were to put a stake in
each corner, that's about 155 ft.
>> What is it from the building?
>> Uh about 2/3 to 3/4 of a mile.
>> Thank you. Any
other questions before we continue?
Please proceed.
>> Mr. President,
um I may share if I could uh some of the
conversations that we've had with other
neighbors. Um we understand that um
we are working with Mr. Galiotus to um
figure out a long-term solution for um
you know potentially
um adjusting the property the way that
it looks. He's a neighboring land owner
and and perhaps there's a way that we
can um you know keep a healthy buffer uh
and ensure that that stays there from to
both our east and north. Um, and we've
also had the uh good privilege of
getting to know Mr. Eley as well and
have had uh had some great conversations
uh with him and his family. And we
we have a substantial amount of land
there that, you know, we don't ever
intend to develop on. Um, and we think
it would be great land to graze.
>> Dr. Rich
>> uh President Crave through you.
Can you remind me? I believe that in a
conversation that we had, Mr. GLMer that
you talked about that this data center
is actually um in a bowl type area. So,
it is not going to have the visible
impact that people were concerned about
with aesthetics.
>> Mr. president through you. We we intend
to use the topography of the property to
uh have as as little impact as possible
to the um to the I I don't even know if
there there there will be any impact to
the horizon, but we we certainly intend
to be well below the uh red flashing
lights of the windmill.
>> Councilman W.
>> Thank you. U Mr. Chair through you. Um
sir, you mentioned that you've had
conversations with Mr. Gallotus and Mr.
Eley. Um are there any discussions or
agreements that have been talked about
or are you close to a resolution with
those land owners? I'm just curious as
to what the progress is, if any.
>> Mr. Mr. President, through you. We we've
had we have not uh we've not executed
any agreements with them. It's it's it's
high level um you know just trying to be
good people working in good faith to um
find the best possible outcome for
everybody.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to build on that
for a moment. Um related to the King
Ranch, um Council Member White, um we
have met with them. There's a strong
desire for the family to use that land
for grazing purposes. Um there's a
strong desire as you just heard from the
folks at this table to maintain the
agriculture custom of the community and
we really you know we were excited about
those discussions because it allowed the
parties to
really achieve the each end goal. The
King Ranch is always needing grass,
additional grass, especially in a
drought year. Keeping the grass grazed
is in everyone's interest related to
fire mitigation.
um allowing the neighbor to use the
grass for the benefit of their operation
is something that really is consistent
with the value system of the company and
then um you know as I mentioned keeping
keeping the custom and culture so that
agreement is you know been discussed
there's a meeting of the minds of the
parties however we're a little bit
premature to be entering into the next
steps until we continue to work um with
the city process
as related to um to Mr. uh Galotus um
again high level discussions
um some con concepts have been you know
discussed those discussions have not
stalled which indicates to me too that
there's healthy productive exchange of
ideas occurring um again not necessarily
sure you know as far as building
agreements contingent on outcomes you
know that that will continue as this
process continues to move forward. But
the lines of communication were opened
with the neighbors immediately. Um I was
really grateful that uh Miss Woodhouse
uh acknowledged that because you know
being a good neighbor, being a good
corporate citizen is absolutely
essential in Wyoming and the folks with
me at the table fully understand that. I
appreciate the the questions from you,
Dr. Aldridge about the the con
conceptual layout and um would like to
extend personally an invitation to all
of any council member that would be
interested to come take a tour to
actually orient yourself as far as where
the bowl is and sort of how the design
intention is to um be utilized for the
benefit of the project. as far as um
trying to use that natural landscape to
avoid sound, light, you know, other
disruption in the community. Um to make
sure that the natural uh you know,
contour of the of the landscape remains,
but using it to the benefit of trying to
um insulate and and give additional um
isolation from any of the the neighbors
that could be aware. So, um, we're happy
to schedule that through, uh, Jennifer
and at your convenience. But I do think
orienting yourselves to the proximity of
the proposed, you know, clustering,
hugging the the roadway, um, as Mr. GMer
explained, um, really is, um, quite
advantageous to the development of the
project as well as to the community.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, President Crave through you. And
looking at the map, it looks like there
are two features that I would assume are
either water retention or detention
ponds. One in the northeast corner and
one to the southwest. Is that correct?
>> Yes, ma'am. Uh, Presidentu, apologies.
Um, President, yes, ma'am. That is
correct. Um, that those are speculative
layout. We would need to actually do
engineering of what does a you know what
does the wershed look like? What is the
natural topography grade like? Where
does the water actually going for where
the detention will be? But you have to
have responsible detention on the site.
Um we're not saving it to use it for any
of our facilities. We won't be doing
anything in it besides uh um storing
water in the event of a flash heavy rain
and it prevents flooding downstream.
That's really the the goal of any of the
detention ponds. That is likely not
where they will go, but it'll go
somewhere along those lines.
>> Question.
>> They'll be close to that. Um, but it'll
be strategically laid out with, you
know, a lot of engineers.
>> I just one quick follow-up question. It
appears, and my eyes, I'm sorry, are
getting old, but I can't read the print
on the diagram from here. Is that small
box towards
um what looks like the one that's gray
to the uh lower is that the office space
there or is the white box the office
space?
>> President you uh the the far west side
that that gray area would be the
operations office building that would be
supplemental to some office in each
building. You'll have full-time staff on
each
>> building, but then like I said, we've
always um underbuilt office um to our
operation staff chagrin. So, we plan to
have some supplemental office space for
them to grow into over time because when
we started out in the industry, you
know, Gordon um 15, you know, 14 years
ago and myself about 8 years ago, it was
low permanent jobs. It was, you know,
maybe 50 to a building at max. And as
the complicated, you know, nature of
these have just gone up and to the right
in an exponential manner, we've also
seen the actual facility staff numbers
climb dramatically, not just from us,
but also the client. Um, so that is the
reason for always now building more
office is year-over-year where the
headcount is getting higher and higher
for them. We can confidently underwrite,
you know, 300 to 500 jobs, but that's
really the reason for the it's most
likely if we were to do it right now
today, staff it, it's probably around
350. But because the amount of headcount
has gone up and up, we say around 500.
It might be six, it might be seven, but
I don't want to overpromise and underdel
um as well. So that's why we say about,
you know, probably 3 to 350, but 3 to
500 is very realistic.
>> One more question,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> President Crave, the bulge that appears
in the roadway um below the center right
here, this one, is this is it bulged out
like this because that's where going the
security gates will be. President. Yes,
ma'am. That's correct. That is exactly
right. Uh and you have some natural
turnarounds for if someone doesn't pass
the security check. You have staging so
that way you have extra parking going
into security so it's not a bottleneck
for deliveries backing up into the road
or anything like that. So you have a
fair amount of extra space and security
for that reason.
>> Councilman Leborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. [clears throat] Chairman.
I'd like to go down and point out a
couple things on that map. I'm
>> sorry. Um,
uh, do we have a speaker there at the
podium?
>> Well, I think we all need to be able to
look at it. Well, I guess that'll do
best we can here. Um
[clears throat]
>> the mention
the mention of the detention ponds and
the whole question of the bowl
raises the question of uh the drainage
from the
uh Sherard treatment plant settling
ponds across this property. And as I
look at it, it comes out right about
here and will go into this zone A, which
I believe is also referred to as uh
Diamond Creek. Comes down and eventually
recharges Crow Creek and a very
important element of keeping that water
in Crow Creek. Now, when I discussed
this with uh the director of the plant
this morning before I got here, he
mentioned that this uh water that comes
out of the settling pond, which is the
idea, it settles out that uh
elements they need to settle out from
the lake water where they mix the lake
water with the Uh
the uh our our field our
>> groundwater
>> well fields up the creek has a future
consideration
of how that's going to happen over time
and whether or not that water can be
utilized. And of course it's very highly
regulated. I discussed this with
Jennifer Ziggman from the uh
[clears throat]
DEEQ water uh department. So, what
consideration has been given
to the fact that this swale
carries
128,000 gallons a day out of that
settling pond and across this property
to eventually the creek.
Mr. President, three, Councilman Labour,
we the goal of any development is just
to maintain the existing flows. We we
wouldn't um as as Jack mentioned, those
are those are just conceptual. We would
need to have some detention for the area
that we impact. But um the the intent
and the goal and this has not been this
has not been fully engineered. And I I
want to make that very clear that this
is we have a we have a lot of
engineering work to do and there's you
know that's that's a happens at a later
inning um if you will but we we those
are those are flood planes and and we do
not we do not develop in flood planes
and we do not adjust um
mess around with trying to reroute the
flood planes or anything like that.
That's smart.
>> And I I hope we'll all go on this tour
that's being s suggested here because uh
I'm fairly familiar with all this. I
served on the uh Warren Air Force Super
Fund cleanup site for 10 years. And so
um a lot of these things are very
important and certainly I'm very aware
of
the importance that we have in our
wellfields immediately downgradient from
our uh landfill which has been a
controversial and longstanding issue.
So, and to their credit, the board of
public utilities and uh their staff have
really looked at
how we can recharge those well fields
and it is not I mean at the present time
uh they've done some pretty high level
study of what exists out there in terms
of uh the geology. And so I the reason I
I mention this fellow council members is
this specific element is very important
to be included in our annexation
because not only do you have the
immediate
factor here of a discharge
through a
basically it's a swale. It's not not
really a defined creek, but it you'll
notice it's very green. And as I pointed
out, it's 128,000 gallons a day. That's
the average comes out of the plant. And
I can tell you that uh
our staff out there was
um
interested. Um I don't think they had
been involved to the degree that we
should have been but uh there's a lot
involved there uh with our extremely
critical water needs of our far-flung
system and how it is mixed and how where
it goes from there. So,
um I'm very interested in more
information about this because I think
we look at this in a way
um
that
past data centers in the immediate
vicinity that would have been developed
in the North Range Park didn't have
these drainage considerations.
This is a creek,
a critical creek that's going to
continue to flow. I mean, our treatment
plant's not going anywhere, and that
flow is essential to that mix process
that they make to meet those standards.
So, um, I just thought it was
appropriate time for me to bring this
up. This is a lot more than a couple of
detention ponds, and this is an expense
that needs to be that needs to be
analyzed and included
because at some point in the future and
I applaud the BOPU for looking at this
and I've been following it for some
years. We need to re we need to have
that ability to recharge those well
fields and the water is
not directly close but it's in the
vicinity. And so I think if you're
talking about piping this, that's that's
a real serious consideration because I I
also would like to point out that uh the
recharge of of this I believe probably
has an effect on the downgradient
neighbors that you just met with. Did
any of them express this concern? M Mr.
President, through you. Um there there's
been a lot of discussion about about
water and our like again I just want to
just want to emphasize what Jack said
this was just conceptual and our our
intent is to is to maintain existing
flows as they are. We don't we don't uh
intend to um
>> Well, thank you.
>> I just wanted to make sure that
>> yeah, we brought that up and
>> as we proceed here, it's uh um a very
serious consideration and also I think
an opportunity but it uh is something
that um [snorts] is unique to that site.
Thank you.
Please go ahead
>> Mr. Uh, President and Council Member
Lebornne, thank you for that discussion.
We very much look to you and your
decades of experience and your
commitment to Cheyenne and topics just
as you expressed. Um, we have a team of
engineers that are very familiar with
the area. They will be working with the
BOPU and to accomplish just as what Mr.
Glistier said. The goal here is not to
disturb, disrupt, rework any type of
existing essential element to the
landscape particularly when it comes to
such a viable you know critical piece of
infrastructure for the you know
functioning of the city. So there's
solutions to be had there's discussions
to that can occur and again we welcome
and look forward to your input and and
your feedback as these conversations
hopefully advance.
Thank you,
>> Mr. President. Through you and the one
thing I would add as well, Councilman
Lebornne, and really appreciate um want
to echo her sentiment uh Sydney
sentiments on thank you all for all your
service. Uh but that is also part of the
benefit of having extra land. We're we
can't possibly develop all of this. It's
it's too much. But it was an all or
nothing. And then it ends up actually as
a pro because it allows us to work
around things like that and not impede
existing operations that are beneficial
and essential to the area, the
community, the neighbors, the you know
water treatment facilities. So that is a
huge pro of having this amount of land
is we can we can adjust around that
accordingly and not impede any existing
operations.
>> Thank you.
>> Go ahead. President you if it's all
right in the interest of time I think
we'd love to jump and just have a little
bit of a discussion around the power.
>> All right.
>> U Mr. President just a question I don't
know how how how long we intend to go
today um because I have some
discussion that may take a period of
time on the annexation and community
benefits agreement and um I don't want
people hopefully jumping out before we
have time to do that. Um,
>> our plan was to go to till one o'clock.
>> That's 10 minutes from now. Um, I have a
document that I want to make sure I get
a chance to hand out and uh, briefly
describe. Um, and um, I attended the
meeting this morning. Um, and so, uh,
obviously you're running the meeting,
but, um, I'd hate to to miss the
opportunity since we have everybody here
to talk about what are the key issues
here, which are what kind of
arrangements are uh, underway to discuss
with the city of uh, an agreement on
this the annexation and community
benefits.
If you'd like to discuss power, go
ahead.
>> Yes, sir. Mr. President, through you um
Councilman Wolf, happy to turn that over
and have that conversation as we welcome
that conversation. I'll make it very
short in the interest of time on power.
Um like I mentioned uh before and you
know Black Hills Energy is one pager, no
rateayer is going to bear a single scent
of this cost. Um it should be actually
increase to the infrastructure in the
area. And then should Black Hills say
have a date that is incredibly far
pushed out from a delivery of power and
we were to do some sort of bridging
solution, we will work with the city and
make sure that we have some sort of
sleing ability to make sure that that uh
tax on the electricity is not missed out
on. That is not lost on us. That that
isn't a tremendous attribute of what our
projects can contribute to the
community. And so that is not lost on us
and we want to be able to work together
on that. and uh any of that would just
be temporary for and then ideally go
through Black Hills and that's what
we're working through with them right
now and they're incredibly receptive
about it and excited about the
opportunity but we would not be in any
sort of you know permanent you know
skybox via west own generation asset
and then uh through you Mr. President
Councilman Wolf happy to turn it over to
the community engagement piece that
you'd like to discuss. Councilman Wolf,
I'm not aware of anything in the
annexation statutes that talk about
community benefit requirements. Can you
help us here?
>> Um, sure, Mr. President. I'd be glad to.
Uh, well, let me hand this out to you
and, uh,
Mr. President, through you.
Um
we're four months into this since we uh
postponed this in April
and um from the beginning we had
discussions with these developers about
uh entering into an annexation and
community benefits agreement.
Uh and um
I understand that they have been working
on that. Uh, I don't know where that
stands. I've not seen a document. Don't
know whether it stands in the developer
lab, in the city attorney's lap, the
mayor's lap, uh, planning and zoning.
But, um, be that as it may, I want to
make sure that as we talk about things
that aren't critical, such as the
mausoleum,
that is not critical to our
considerations under the annexations.
Um, we should talk about the things that
are critical to an annexation and to
describing in detail in writing what the
obligations of the developers are and
the obligations of the city. So, in the
absence of uh a document from anybody
else, I sat down with AI the other night
and drafted one. And I did that because
you can talk about these things
conceptually, but until you actually
start looking at the language of what
these things can be, you don't really
have a clear sense of them. And so um I
think as a lawyer but also just as a
member of the council that it is
necessary for us under the schedule that
we have that is going to take this to
final conclusion at the end of
September.
So having four months go by and then be
here at the end of August and being
asked to approve this within the next
month. We either have to get cracking on
this or we have to postpone the final
vote on it or the council has to just
decide
as they did in Microsoft that it's not
important. But for the community, I
think it's incredibly important. So, if
I might before we get done at 1:00 go
through the sort of key elements of this
because you can talk all day and fuss
around with the topography and the water
drainage, but that's a small aspect of
this data center and the issues that it
brings forward to us in this annexation.
And I say this all without being
critical of these three gentlemen and of
my dear friend and colleague Cindy
Delansancy
because they have done a terrific job of
talking to the community of being
accessible of having these open houses
of describing what they're doing.
But as we look at that, Mr. president
and members of the council, we got to
understand
from a legal matter sort of how this all
shapes up because these folks you have
to look at, and I say this not to
disparrage them, but they're flippers.
That's their job. They come in, put
together a project, and then find
the really deep pockets to come and take
it over and operate it. That poses some
very interesting legal issues as we the
council deal with them at this point but
foresee that they end up being replaced
by somebody else some much larger likely
company that's going to operate this. So
if I might let me let me just share with
you my thinking on this. Interestingly,
I asked AI to create a summary of this.
The summary was back basically longer
than the document itself because you can
put these understandings in six pages as
I did and a couple attachments which are
the legal description and and some other
things. But the key issues are the ones
that really want to talk about. We
started talking about them in this
meeting just a few minutes ago. Um, and
so the the sort of the first issue you
have to grapple with is who are we
dealing with? Um, as you can see, and I
gave Mr. Delansancy a copy of this. Um,
you want to bring in everybody, which is
both the developers and the ultimate
users of this. And to do that, you need
to make a document that actually runs
with the land and is binding on anybody
who's going to be involved with the the
project and the land on which it sits.
So that's really the first page
uh and into the parts of the second
page. Then you describe the obligations
of the city and the obligations of the
city are not enormous. Uh at this point
they are we supply you we annex the
property. We zone it for business park
as you are requesting and we agree to
supply water, sewer, police, fire other
things you can articulate.
Then we come to the questions of what
are the obligations of the developers
and this is where um I was watching the
news this morning and they were talking
about prenuptual agreements and I sort
of it's a good analogy for what we've
done. We've been in this sort of
marriage with data centers for the last
couple years now and you start into
these things and everybody's in love
with each other and you don't really
worry about the details. But as we the
council gets more sophisticated and
deals with these companies and deals
in a with some of the problems that we
obviously are seeing and deals with a
kind of sense of the sort of cynicism
that has arrived around data centers in
the last six months or in 2026.
Then you'd try to decide, okay, what do
we need in writing from them? Because
it's all well and good to have them say,
well, we're going to pay for all the
costs of our infrastructure, but you
want to put that in writing and that's
what we need to do and that's what we
haven't been doing. Um, so I've tried to
articulate those. Closed water loop
recirculation, mandatory,
prohibition on evaporative cooling,
mandatory,
emergency power backup, no diesel
generators. And I got a very very
smart and sophisticated answer from
their engineer right here as we talked
about that this morning. But from a
standpoint of environmental protection
for the city of Cheyenne and Laramie
County, we shouldn't want should not
want
backup power being supplied by diesel
generators unless
we agree with you that that's absolutely
essential for a whole bunch of reasons
which might include national security.
President Crave, I believe that um this
is really not an appropriate discussion
to have at this juncture. We have
already voted this down when we were in
talking about Microsoft and that this is
an intrusion on the work session that
was planned for these individuals um to
present to us and I I think this is an
appropriate time to discuss this.
>> Mr. Chairman, as a council,
>> Mr. President,
>> just a moment please. Can I answer her?
I agree with Dr. Aldridge. This was
their opportunity to present their
progress with the neighbors, etc. This
is a
hilarious
>> a proposal that you have brought before
and you I'm sure you'll bring it again.
Uh but that's not the intent of this
work session. Councilman Lebornne.
[cough]
>> Mr. President. [clears throat] Well, my
understanding of work sessions and I've
been here for many obviously
is to educate the council and thereby
through communication like I see here
from the media of the conditions of that
that are responsible
uh for us to evaluate in uh in regard to
the situation. And let me say I'm very
interested in the idea that the previous
annexation with Microsoft is some sign
of some sort of a
binding reference point or uh it was an
action we took.
I hope we learned a lot from it.
But it is entirely appropriate
for us to have this consideration here.
And I appreciate Mr. Wol's efforts.
>> I would call for a vote. President
Crave,
>> Mr. Mr. Chairman, let me let me respond
to Councilwoman.
>> President Cra,
>> let me stop.
>> Everybody stop.
>> This was a presentation by the developer
on their progress. It had nothing to do
with your proposed amendment. That will
come, I'm sure. Um, so I'm I'm going to
agree with Dr. Aldridge that this is not
appropriate at this time. I want to give
it back to the developer to finalize
your presentation
and then we'll wrap it up. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
>> You missed the beginning of their
presentation to the community which
starts with a discussion about what
they're doing to develop an agreement
with the city. That is an adherent part
of their presentation to us. And why
don't you just ask them where we stand
on that?
>> Councilman Wolf, this is their show
today. If they want to discuss that,
that's fine.
>> This is our show, Mr. President.
>> This is This is Councilman Wolf.
Councilman Wolf, you're out of order.
>> Mr. President, thank you members of the
council. Hopefully I can bring us back
on to discussion. We do have an
agreement. We've been working really
hard on this agreement for the past four
months. We have, you have seen me sit in
almost every single council meeting that
you have had to listen, to learn, to
observe, to see the points that are of
interest to you, to learn the needs, to
make sure that we can be the best and
most responsible partner with the city
that we can be as we can go forward. So,
I look forward to reading uh and and
learning more about Council Member
Wolf's um document, but I've brought my
own today. And it's something that we've
been working really really hard on. And
I think that there's a lot of
similarities between the concerns that
uh Council Member Wolf has as well as
those of us at this table. We do worry
about the details. We do want to make
sure that we get things right. So what
we have put together we have titled a
commitment to the Cheyenne community and
basically what this document walks
through and I'm happy to do it in the in
the moments that we have left here but
what it does is it outlines at this
stage in the process we are at an
annexation and a zone change discussion.
That's it. What we can be able to have a
discussion around at this point in the
proceeding to identify what the project
is and what the project is not. And
really the goal of us bringing that
forward to you is to be fully
transparent with the community to
address the concerns that Council Member
Wolf and Council Member Lebornne are
having around what is it that we're even
talking about? Do we do we feel that
this is a good fit for our community or
do we not? And by having that measuring
stick, if you will, to see what is the
intention. Um I I respectfully disagree
that we're house flippers on this
project. We're building a project for a
tenant to ultimately be a a partner in,
but we want to be proud of our work and
we think that by outlining this
commitment and if u with with your
indulgence um Mr. President that I could
just walk you through quickly the
material terms of which all of you will
get a copy of. Um we've been working
very closely with city staff um and just
really trying to find a way, you know,
we're breaking new trail here. This is
not required by any, you know, anything
out there as far as regulation. We're
voluntaries, voluntarily subjecting
oursel to be part of this process. And
maybe we're somewhat of a guinea pig and
sometimes it takes a little bit of time
to to find, you know, the the right
temperature of the porridge, if you
will, that it's not too much or too
little. And that's what we've been
working towards. So with on that note,
um we have created a commitment to the
Cheyenne community. The um document
starts with several recitals very much
like council member Wolves does and I'll
just kind of skip right to the sort of
meat of the of the proposal is there's a
description of the project and its
intended uses. We clearly outline
everything you've heard today about what
we're doing as far as building in phases
and you know um what we intend to use
the project of. Then we march down to a
community impact disclosure.
And that's where we really walk through
and we say, "Here's what the jobs are
going to be. Here's what the traffic
impacts are going to be. Here's what the
environmental impacts are going to be
and what we're going to do about them."
And then there then the next section
walks us through development
restrictions.
These are things that again guard rails
in the process that we are agreeing that
the following development restriction
shall apply to the project not may shall
apply to the project. Uh we walk through
what the water usage is going to be. We
talk about you know that there is no
evaporative air cooled and only closed
loop cooling systems or other comp
comparable technology advances that use
less or the same amount of water.
meaning that we're we're we're making
the the the obligation even tighter, not
making it wider. We're making we're
voluntarily making it tighter. Um we're
talking about where industrial water
shall not be discharged into public
systems without third party testing and
approval if tested with compliance with
city water standards. I think you heard
uh Mr. O'Neal discuss this morning that
wastewater won't even be on the table
for discussion related to this project.
cooling systems and power usage. We talk
about that. We talk about lighting. We
know that lighting has been an a an
enormous concern for your constituents
in this community. We don't want to do
anything that adds to a problem. We want
to be the the the people that find the
solution. So, we march through what our
answer to that is. Sound. We know sound
has been another large topic. Again,
I've sat in these meetings with you.
I've listened. I know what the feelings
of the neighbors are and we're trying to
get ahead of all this to be the best
neighbor and corporate citizen that we
can be. Setbacks, again, we march
through the setbacks. Go above and
beyond what the current code requires.
Landscaping, again, trying to be
extremely sensitive knowing that every
drop of water that we have and our
community means so much to all of us.
finding a way to keep the area beautiful
and and and maintain the custom and
culture of the community without being
wasteful of water. We outline that. And
then we talk about our community
contribution and that we will be able to
get to that place where when we're
operational and actually have a project
and a revenue stream is very hard to
make commitments for financial you know
you know drill down to make financial
commitments when at this point we don't
know that we that we're even going to
have a project but the commitment is
there that should we have a project
should we get forward that this
discussion will absolutely be revisited
as soon as we can. what we would do with
our trash, what we're going to do with
workforce housing, what we're going to
do with road modification, snow plowing,
fire mitigation, and you know, just just
continue to try to hash out some of the
details that council member Wolf has
raised in his version of the document.
So, again, I know that uh that time is
short, but I do look forward to maybe
having a meeting of the minds and
looking at both documents and seeing if
there's things that we could pick and
choose as we come back to uh in the
future. But we have listened to the
discussions. We do know that this is
something that is important to you. We
feel that we've worked really hard with
our version of of this document and uh
we hope that between now and when we see
you again that you'll all have the
opportunity to review it, digest it,
discuss it, and hopefully that we are in
a good place as we move forward.
>> Thank you so much. And President Cave
through you. Uh thank you all for the
time. I know we're a little bit over so
appreciate all the time and effort here.
um on a on a Friday afternoon. Um the
one comment I'd like to add is that we
we build, develop, operate, entitle, and
own data centers long term. Um we still
have operational data centers. Happy to
introduce anybody to anyone from our
operation staff that's worked for us for
how long has James worked for us? 12
years. 12 years. Um we have long-term
operational staffs. We stay involved in
these projects. We don't build it or
entitle it, sell it, and and head out
and say, "Good luck with the next
group." um we are here for a long-term
investment and that is what we've done
in you know the communities we've
invested in and had the opportunity to
build in. So any building we've built
we've stayed in um for a long period of
time for a very long period of time. And
so again thank you all for the time the
effort. We really appreciate y'all being
willing to work with us today. Uh we
look forward to future conversation.
Please do not hesitate to reach out
should there be any questions, concerns,
we are available to not only y'all but
any of your constituents as well. Should
any constituents in your, you know,
different wards, just even a friend in
one of the counties, please refer them
to us, Wyoming at skyboxdatenters.com.
We also have a local area code phone
number that goes to Tom and myself. Um,
this is not the last conversation. This
won't be the last conversation even
should we get entitled. We will have
conversations for years to come and we
want to be quick to listen, slow to
speak, and good business stewards, but
also, you know, good citizens of the
community on both sides. So really
appreciate the time. Thank you all.
>> Thank you very much. We appreciate your
presentation today. With that, uh, we're
adjourned.